Continuous speech recognition has had a rocky history.
连续语音识别的发展历程很是坎坷
In the early 1970's,
在 20 世纪 70 年代初期
the United States funded ASR research with a DARPA challenge.
美国借助 DARPA 挑战赛资助了 ASR 的研究 (该挑战赛由美国国防部高级研究计划局 DARPA 资助)
The goal was to develop a recognizer for a 1000 word vocabulary.
当时的资助目标是开发一个能识别 1000 个单词的识别器
The goal was achieved a few years later by Carnegie-Mellon's Harpy System.
几年后 卡内基梅隆大学的 Harpy 系统实现了这个目标
But the future prospects were disappointing and funding dried up.
但前景不佳 而且资金也耗尽了
This was the start of the first big AI Winter.
由此 AI 第一个真正的冬天到来了
Performance improved in the 80's and 90's with refinement of probabilistic models.
80 和 90 年代 概率模型的改进提高了 AI 的性能
More recently computing power has made
再近些年 由于计算能力的提高
larger dimensions in neural network modeling a reality.
神经网络模型得以建立更多维数
So what makes speech recognition hard?
那语音识别的难点在哪呢？
The first set of problems to solve are related to
第一批难点在
the audio signal itself, noise for instance.
音频信号本身 比如噪声、
Cars going by, clocks ticking, other people talking,
经过的汽车声、时钟的滴答声、他人的谈话声、
microphones static, our ASR has to know
麦克风静电干扰等等 ASR 需要知道
which parts of the audio signal matter and which parts to discard.
哪部分音频信号是它需要的 哪部分又是该舍弃的
Variability of pitch.
音高的不同
Variability of volume.
音量的不同
One speaker sounds different than another even when saying the same word.
虽然在说同一个单词 讲话者的声音也会不同
The pitch and loudness at least in English don't change
最起码在英语里 音高和音量
the ground truth of which word was spoken.
不会影响单词的意思
If I say hello,
就算我用不同的方式说
or hello, or hello.
“你好”
It's all the same word and spelling.
我说的都是同一个单词 同一种拼写
We could even think of these differences as
因此 我们甚至可以把这种差异当作
another kind of noise that needs to be filtered out.
另一种需要过滤的噪声
Variability of words speed.
语速的不同
Words spoken at different speeds need to be aligned and matched.
我们需要对齐并匹配以不同语速说出的单词
If I say speech or speech,
用不同的语速说 “演讲”
it's still the same word with the same number of letters.
指的都是同一个单词 字母数也是一样的
It's up to the ASR to align the sequences of sound correctly.
因此 ASR 需要把声音序列正确地对齐起来
Word boundaries.
单词边界
When we speak words run from one to the next without pause.
当我们说“不停顿地说出一连串单词” 时
We don't separate them naturally.
我们不会故意一字一顿地说话
Humans understand it because we already
人类能听懂这个句子
know that the word boundaries should be in certain places.
因为我们已经知道什么地方该是单词的边界
This brings us to another class of problems that are language or knowledge related.
这就又给我们带来了一类难题 和语言或知识有关
The fact is, humans perceive speech with more than just their ears.
事实上 人类获取语音的途径并不只是耳朵
We have domain knowledge of our language that allows us
我们是有语言知识域的
to automatically sort out ambiguities as we hear them.
这个知识域让我们得以自动判断那些模棱两可的话是什么意思
Words that sound the same but have different spellings.
听起来一样但拼写不一样的单词
Word groups that are reasonable in one context but not in another.
在一种语境里有意义但在其它语境无意义的词群
Here's a classic example.
举一个典型的例子
When I say recognize speech,
当我用英语说 "recognize speech"（“识别语音”）的时候
it sounds a lot like recognize speech.
听起来很像 "wreck a nice beach"（“破坏美丽的沙滩”）
But you knew what I meant because you know I'm discussing speech recognition.
但你知道我的意思 因为你知道我在讲语音识别
The context matters.
所以语境很重要
An inference like this is going to be tricky for a computer model.
要让计算机模型实现这种推断是个难点
Another aspect to consider.
还有一个方面要考虑
Spoken language is different than written language.
口语和书面语不同
There are hesitations, repetitions, fragments of sentences,
说口语时 我们会犹豫、重复、只说只词片语、
slips of the tongue,
口误
a human listener is able to filter this out.
人类听者可以将这些干扰过滤掉
Imagine a computer that only knows language from audio books and newspapers read aloud.
但想象计算机只从有声书和报纸音频里学习语言
Such a system may have a hard time decoding unexpected sentence structures.
这种系统估计很难对意料之外的句子结构进行解码
Okay, we've identified lots of problems to solve here.
好了 我们已经提出了很多要解决的问题了
Variability of pitch, volume, and speed,
音高、音量和语速的不同
ambiguity due to word boundaries, spelling, and context.
单词界限、拼写和语境造成的语义模糊
We're going to introduce some ways to solve
接下来我们要介绍几种办法
these problems with a number of models and technologies.
来解决这些问题 我们会用到若干模型和技术
We'll start at the beginning with the voice itself.
先从语音本身开始学习吧